Leon Hale Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Leon Hale Papers
1923-2002
Hale, Leon, 1921-
Documentation of the career of Texas journalist and prose writer, Leon Hale. Central to this career, since 1956, is his work as a regular "roving Texas" columnist and chronicler for the Houston Post and Houston Chronicle.
16 boxes, 17 linear feet
2001-004
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Biographical Note
Leon Hale is a widely read and longtime columnist for the Houston Chronicle. He makes his home in Houston but spends much time at Winedale (near Round Top, TX) and Santa Fe, NM. Hale is a master at recounting tales of and reflections upon life and times in rural 20th Century Texas. He conveys all his subject's charm in the colloquial language, salty wit, and country humor that he uses so well. He is the father of Mark and Rebecca and the husband of Babette Fraser Hale.
Born May 30, 1921, at Stephenville, Texas, Leon Hale was reared in 22 different houses in nine different West Texas towns, from Fort Worth to Lubbock. His father was a store clerk and traveling salesman, but most of his relatives were farmers and his early background is entirely rural. Hale graduated from Eastland, Texas High School in 1939, entered Texas Tech at Lubbock and served 3 years in the U.S Army Air Forces before returning to "Tech" to take a journalism degree in 1946.
Hale began his journalism career as assistant editor for the Texas A&M University Extension Service, 1946-47, and progressed as follows: farm and ranch editor for the Houston Post, 1948-52; magazine editor for Humble Oil & Refining Co., 1953-55; "roving Texas columnist" for the Houston Post, 1956-1983; and since 1983, columnist for the Houston Chronicle. In addition, he has served as part-time instructor at Sam Houston State University, contributed to Texas Parade magazine, written free-lance articles, authored ten books and contributed to many others. Mr. Hale's awards include recognition by the Headliners Foundation of Texas and AP and UPI wire services. He also received the Jesse H. Jones Award for Fiction from the Texas Institute of Letters for one of his two novels.
Scope and Contents
This set of papers documents Leon Hale's long and prolific writing career that began in 1946. It is divided into ten major categories with the bulk of the material being comprised of Mr. Hale's book projects, daily columns, letters from readers, and miscellaneous articles. The materials are housed in sixteen boxes, including fourteen record cartons and two oversized boxes. Each of the categories is prefaced by a detailed description.
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Subjects (Persons)
Hale, Leon
Formats
Correspondence; Typescript drafts; Galley Proofs
Acquisition:
Donated by creator, 2001
Detailed Description
- Book Projects, 1963-1997 (Box 1-3)
  The materials in this section are housed in three cartons and represent eight different volumes published by Leon Hale. The materials include correspondence with editors/publishers, business/legal documents, notes, outlines, manuscripts, typescripts, proof copies, reviews, promotions, letters from readers and even screenplays. The bulk of the material represents Hale's work on two novels, Bonney's Place and Addison.
  - Turn South at the Second Bridge - 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1-16)
    - Doubleday letters & statements. 1963-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Hale letters to Doubleday. 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Doubleday business documents. 1963-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Character list and other notes. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Chapters outline. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Chapters III & IV - typescript w/corrections. no date (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Answer to queries from editor. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Typescript - chapters I - XII. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8-13)
    - Reviews and Promotions. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Letters regarding - miscellaneous. 1963-2001 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Texas A & M reprint project. 1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bonney's Place - 1972 (Box 1, Folder 17-31)
    - Letters from Doubleday. 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Hale letters to Doubleday. 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Doubleday business documents. 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Outline. no date (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Early typescript fragment. no date (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Final galley proof. 1971 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Foundry proof. 1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Reviews and Promotions. 1972 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Letters from readers. 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Alternative dust jacket drawing from reader. 1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence regarding film rights. 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Film rights business documents. 1977 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Screenplay based on novel. 1986 (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
    - Popular library letters about paper edition. 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Addison - 1979 (Box 1-2)
    - Initial proposal by Leon Hale. no date (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Sample pages initially submitted. no date (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Letters from Doubleday. 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Hale letters to Doubleday. 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Doubleday business documents. 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence with Philip Spitzer. 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Outline. 1978 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Manuscript draft fragments. no date (Box 1, Folder 39-43)
    - Editing Notes. no date (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Early typescript w/corrections. no date (Box 1, Folder 45-48)
    - Later typescript w/corrections. no date (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
    - An original typescript of final draft. no date (Box 2, Folder 5-8)
    - Final galley proof. 1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Foundry proof. 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Dust jackets. 1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Letters from readers. 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Reviews and Promotions. 1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Texas Institute of Letter's award announcement letter. 1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Screenplay Based on Novel. 1982 (Box 2, Folder 15-17)
  - A Smile from Katie Hattan & Other Natural Wonders - 1982 (Box 2, Folder 18-37)
    - Tentative outline. no date (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Columns chosen for chapters I - XVI. 1982 (Box 2, Folder 19-34)
    - Galley proof w/corrections. 1982 (Box 2, Folder 35-37)
  - Easy Going - 1983 (Box 2, Folder 38-49)
    - Columns chosen for sections I - XIII. 1983 (Box 2, Folder 38-49)
  - Paper Hero - 1986 (Box 3, Folder 1-12)
    - Notes and Revisions. 1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Early draft - typescript. 1986 (Box 3, Folder 2-5)
    - Later draft - typescript. 1986 (Box 3, Folder 6-9)
    - Galley proof w/corrections. 1986 (Box 3, Folder 10-12)
  - Texas Chronicles - 1989 (Box 3, Folder 13-26)
    - Galley proof. 1989 (Box 3, Folder 13-19)
    - Uncorrected proof copy. 1989 (Box 3, Folder 20-26)
  - Home Spun - 1997 (Box 3, Folder 27-37)
    - Working notes. 1997 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Winedale Press documents. 1997 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Final Manuscript - second draft. 1997 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Corrected proof copy - sections I - III. 1997 (Box 3, Folder 30-34)
    - First uncorrected proof copy w/print wrappers. 1997 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Second uncorrected proof copy w/print wrappers. 1997 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Dust jacket proofs. 1997 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Articles and Short Stories, 1946-2000, 92 items (Box 4, Folder 1-42)
  This section includes articles and short stories, other than his regular column, authored or edited by Mr. Hale from 1946-2000. Included are manuscripts, typescripts and printed items.
  - Manuscript (Box 4, Folder 1-19)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts. 48 items. 1960-2000 (Box 4, Folder 1-19)
  - Printed (Box 4, Folder 20-42)
    - Southern Living. 1 item. 1983 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Vision. 1 item. 1978 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Vista. 3 items. 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 22-23)
    - Texas Parade. 14 items. 1966-1973 (Box 4, Folder 24-32)
    - Texas Living, Houston Post. 1 item. 1952 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Humble Farm Family. 22 items. 1948-1959 (Box 4, Folder 34-41)
    - Annual Report, A&M Extension Service. 1 item. 1946 (Box 4, Folder 42)
- Notes, no dates (Box 4, Folder 43-51)
  These folders hold pages from nine different legal pads that were filled with manuscript notations by Leon Hale. The content appears to be random, varied, and without date or formal arrangement.
  - Miscellaneous Manuscript Notes (Box 4, Folder 43-51)
    - Working notes on ruled paper. no dates (Box 4, Folder 43-51)
- Address Books and Calendars, 1973-2000, 25 items (Box 4, OVS 1-OVS 2)
  Includes 3 different address books and 22 calendars. Only one of the address books is dated, 1976. The calendars span the years 1973-1981 and 1988-2000. The two varieties of wall calendars typically note column subjects, appointments and appearances for each day.
  - Address Books (Box 4, Folder 52-54)
    - Address books. 3 items. 1976-? (Box 4, Folder 52-54)
  - Calendars (Box OVS 1-OVS 2)
    - Houston Post wall calendars. 9 items. 1973-1981 (Box OVS 1, Folder 1-9)
    - Year-at-a-Glance, laminated calendars. 13 items. 1988-2000 (Box OVS 2)
- Photographic Materials, 1964-1998 (Box 5, Folder 1-26)
  This set of photographs falls roughly into two categories: file or publicity shots of Mr. Hale and shots of people, places, things, and events that interested or inspired him in his work. The bulk of the photos are black and white. Those photos not of Hale appear to have been shot by him.
  - Prints (Box 5, Folder 1-25)
    - Animals, rural. [black & white]. 1973 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Artwork. [black & white]. no dates (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Buildings, rural. [black & white]. 1973-1977 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Contact sheet, misc. images. [black & white]. no dates (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Folks, identified. [black & white]. 1964-1977 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Folks, unidentified. [black & white]. 1973-1977 (Box 5, Folder 6-9)
    - Leon Hale, file photos. [black & white]. no dates (Box 5, Folder 10-13)
    - Leon Hale, file photos. [color]. 1966-1998 (Box 5, Folder 14-19)
    - Leon Hale and other folks. [black & white]. 1966-1973 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Houston Post shots, Al Shire. [black & white]. 1998 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Landscapes, rural. [black & white]. 1972-1974 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous snapshots. [color]. no dates (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Scheller's Place. [black & white]. no dates (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Leon Hale, candid. 1973 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Negatives (Box 5, Folder 25-26)
    - Black & white. no dates (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Color. No dates (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Incoming Correspondence, 1957-2001, 426 items (Box 6, Folder 1-55)
  These are letters sent to Leon Hale over more than forty years. Most of them are laudatory but a few are critical. Many of them are one-time missives from loyal readers but there are as many as 145 from the most prolific of the correspondents. Some also appear to be from friends or acquaintances. Among them are letters from John Henry Faulk and Louie Welch.
  - Letters from Twiss Butler. 4 items. 1975-1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Letter from Colleen's Books. 1 item. 1975 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Letter from John Henry Faulk. 1 item. 1977 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Letter from Pinky Hull. 1 item. 1986 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Letters from Pud Joines. 7 items. 1975-1978 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Letter from Brad Justice. 1 item. 1975 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Letters from Jim McMahon. 5 items. 1966 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Letters from O. F. Morgan. 4 items. 1990s (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Letters from Bill Puckett. 7 items. 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Letters from Spradlin Family. 4 items. 1970 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Letters from R. R. Riley. 5 items. 1959 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Letters from Robert C. Roach. 145 items. 1974-1994 (Box 6, Folder 12-23)
  - Letter from Louie Welch. 1 item. 1976 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous letters. 30 items. No Dates (Box 6, Folder 25-31)
  - Miscellaneous letters. 210 items. 1957-2001 (Box 6, Folder 32-55)
- Scrapbooks, 1948, 2 items (Box 7)
  These two scrapbooks were carefully constructed from the clipped articles authored by Leon Hale during his 1948 tenure as Houston Post, Farm and Ranch Editor.
  - Houston Post Farm & Ranch Editor Articles (Box 7)
    - Volume I. 1948 (Box 7)
    - Volume II. 1948 (Box 7)
- Leon Hale Columns, Houston Post, 1948-2002 (Box 8-11)
  The bulk of Leon Hale's columns, printed over 54 years, will be found in this group. The acidic and crumbling newsprint clippings have been photocopied for the sake of preservation, and arranged chronologically by year. Six binders are filled with typescripts of various columns that have been thematically grouped by the author.
  - Photocopies of Columns [clipped, sorted by month and year] (Box 8-10)
    - Photocopies of printed columns. 1948-1969 (Box 8, Folder 1-32)
    - Photocopies of printed columns. 1970-1976 (Box 9, Folder 1-27)
    - Photocopies of printed columns. 1977-2002 (Box 10, Folder 1-41)
  - Binders of Selected Columns [grouped by Leon Hale] (Box 11, Folder 1-6)
    - Typescripts of columns [binders 1-3]. No Dates (Box 11, Folder 1-3)
    - Typescripts of columns [binders 4-6]. 1964-1995 (Box 11, Folder 4-6)
- Awards and Artifacts, 1972-1992, 10 items (Box 12, Folder 1-10)
  There are eight wall-plaque type awards presented to Leon Hale, together with two small wooden carvings crafted by him.
  - Awards (Box 12, Folder 1-8)
    - Wall-plaque awards. 8 items. 1972-1992 (Box 12, Folder 1-8)
  - Artifacts (Box 12, Folder 9-10)
    - Wood carvings by Leon Hale. 2 items. 1942 (Box 12, Folder 9-10)
- Collected Materials, 1923-2001 (Box 4, 7, 13-14, OVS 1)
  This large group of materials is composed of items collected but not created by Leon Hale. It includes books, articles, subject files, newspaper sections, posters, work created by others, audio and video recordings. These materials were collected on the basis of their importance as information, ephemeral memorabilia or project documentation.
  - Books (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Books donated - catalog records. 26 items. 1972-2000 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Printed Articles (Box 4, Folder 56-57)
    - Articles about Leon Hale. 12 items. 1947-2000 (Box 4, Folder 56-57)
  - Subject Files (Box 13, Folder 1-47)
    - Files Including Letters from Leon Hale. 1965-1980 (Box 13, Folder 1-13)
      - Bits & Pieces - Jokes & Quotes [notes]. no dates (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Camp Creek property. 1966-1974 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Jokes and Yarns [notes]. no dates (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Mark & Joanne [Hale]. 1970-1974 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - C. E. Morgan's "witches" project. 1966-1973 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Jack Sander's book project. 1965-1967 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Buck Schiwetz and Sharon Steen [miscellaneous]. 1976-1979 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Buck Schiwetz interview and Hale article. 1975 (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Buck Schiwetz Memories project. 1977-1978 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Philip Spitzer file [literary agent]. 1973-1974 (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Talking with Texas Writers: Twelve Interviews project. 1979-1980 (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Texas Out Back project. 1974 (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - War Stories column conflict. 1978 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Files. 1941-1990 (Box 13, Folder 14-47)
      - Bozo Texina and other railroad information. 1974 (Box 13, Folder 14)
      - George Bush Presidential Library [UH proposal]. 1990 (Box 13, Folder 15)
      - Jimmy Carter articles [clipped]. 1970s (Box 13, Folder 16)
      - Cartoons, original by Bud Bentley, (B.B.) No Dates (Box 13, Folder 17)
      - Clippings, miscellaneous. 1956-1990 (Box 13, Folder 18)
      - England and France, [trip]. 1994 (Box 13, Folder 19)
      - Hale family mineral rights business. 1973-1974 (Box 13, Folder 20)
      - Leon Hale's favorite columns [from his office wall]. 1976-1984 (Box 13, Folder 21)
      - Houston Post employment business. 1968-1974 (Box 13, Folder 22)
      - Hurricane tracking chart. 1977 (Box 13, Folder 23)
      - Industry, Texas, first-day-of-issue envelope. 1976 (Box 13, Folder 24)
      - Mailing Lists, miscellaneous. do dates (Box 13, Folder 25)
      - Joe Marlarney's Texas Living columns and illustrations. 1952 (Box 13, Folder 26)
      - James Foster McSwill [farce]. 1965-1970 (Box 13, Folder 27)
      - Mimi's songs no dates (Box 13, Folder 28)
      - The Old House Journal. 1978 (Box 13, Folder 29)
      - Promotions, advertisements and clippings. 1969-? (Box 13, Folder 30)
      - Real estate, reply to inquiry. 1979 (Box 13, Folder 31)
      - Recipes. no dates (Box 13, Folder 32)
      - Reprints, miscellaneous. 1973 (Box 13, Folder 33)
      - Shearer Publishing royalty statements. 1996-1997 (Box 13, Folder 34)
      - Southern Living's Southern Journal articles [clipped]. 1982 (Box 13, Folder 35)
      - Taping for the blind. 1970-1973 (Box 13, Folder 36)
      - Texas A & M versus UH program. 1961 (Box 13, Folder 37)
      - Texas Books in Review, Vol. 1, No. 1. 1977 (Box 13, Folder 38)
      - Texas Community Improvement Program Newsletter. 1973 (Box 13, Folder 39)
      - Texas Folk Life Festival. 1973 (Box 13, Folder 40)
      - Texas Institute of Letters. 1955-1974 (Box 13, Folder 41)
      - Texas Writer's Roundup. 1972 (Box 13, Folder 42)
      - Tex-Mex Cookbook. 1971 (Box 13, Folder 43)
      - Val Verde Goatskin Corset Works. 1951-1972 (Box 13, Folder 44)
      - Victoria, Texas API speakers list. 1969 (Box 13, Folder 45)
      - World War II flying lessons I. 1941-1943 (Box 13, Folder 46)
      - World War II flying lessons II. 1941-1943 (Box 13, Folder 47)
  - Newspapers, Special Editions and Sections (Box OVS 1, Folder 1-26)
    - Houston Post, 70th anniversary edition. 1955 (Box OVS 1, Folder 1-12)
    - Houston Post, Golden Crescent edition. 1956 (Box OVS 1, Folder 13-17)
    - Houston Press, 50th anniversary edition. 1961 (Box OVS 1, Folder 18-24)
    - Houston Press, Pictorial History of Hurricane Carla.1961 (Box OVS 1, Folder 25)
    - Houston Chronicle, D-Day, 50 Years Later.1994 (Box OVS 1, Folder 26)
  - Posters (Box OVS 1, Folder 27-33)
    - Events and publications involving Leon Hale. 7 items. 1982-2001 (Box OVS 1, Folder 27-33)
  - Manuscript Materials by Others (Box 7, 13)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts. 23 items. 1923-1984 (Box 13, Folder 48-67)
    - Binder 1. Ralph Robertson's Memories.1995 (Box 7)
    - Binder 2. Ralph Robertson's Old Tales from the Kitchen Table.1997 (Box 7)
  - Audio Recordings (Box 14, Folder 1-32)
    - Spoken Word (Box 14, Folder 1-20)
      - "Endangered Species: Old Time Consensus. no date (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Hell Sermon. 1987 (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - Alonso Hinson Funeral. no date (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - Home Spun read by Leon Hale. 1997 (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - I Saw Heaven. no date (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Marvin's World, A & B. no dates (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - From Mimi. no date (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - Aunt Minnie. no date (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Wyatt Moore, A - E. 1981-1982 (Box 14, Folder 9)
      - Bettie Olney. 1963 (Box 14, Folder 10)
      - David Owen: the Shooting. no date (Box 14, Folder 11)
      - Plain Talk read by Leon Hale. 1991 (Box 14, Folder 12)
      - Wylie Price, A & B. no date (Box 14, Folder 13)
      - Martha Riggs Rogers. no date (Box 14, Folder 14)
      - Rural Chat. no date (Box 14, Folder 15)
      - Aunt Ruth & Aunt Arda. no date (Box 14, Folder 16)
      - Don Swaim - Book Beat.1983 (Box 14, Folder 17)
      - Pauline Wharton. no date (Box 14, Folder 18)
      - Vernon Marie Fitzgerald Schuder. 1975 (Box 14, Folder 19)
      - Texas Bound - short stories. no date (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Musical (Box 14, Folder 21-32)
      - Elbert Brown, piano. 2002 (Box 14, Folder 21)
      - Cowboy music. no date (Box 14, Folder 22)
      - Cowboy song. no date (Box 14, Folder 23)
      - Gabby's Cowboy Corral. no date (Box 14, Folder 24)
      - Jim Hutcheson, original songs. 1991 (Box 14, Folder 25)
      - Ima Ruth, A - C. 1974-1988 (Box 14, Folder 26)
      - Ima Ruth, Tape B, duplicate. 1974 (Box 14, Folder 27)
      - Oscar Peterson. 1986 (Box 14, Folder 28)
      - Scheller's Place, A - B. 1976 (Box 14, Folder 29)
      - Rare songs from 78 rpms. 1999 (Box 14, Folder 30)
      - Saloon. no date (Box 14, Folder 31)
      - Dr. Stumm's Theme. no date (Box 14, Folder 32)
  - Video Recordings (Box 14, Folder #1-#3)
    - E. M. Schiwetz. no date (Box 14, Folder #1)
    - Steam locomotives. no date (Box 14, Folder #2)
    - Where the River Flows North. no date (Box 14, Folder #3)